if you're trying to build a desktop
application in C++ finding a good GUI
framework to use can be tricky I mean
don't get me wrong there are so many
different options out there you could
use something like qt or WX widgets I
mean they seem to be popular they're
crossplatform what's the problem the
problem is I hate them I mean does
anybody actually have a good experience
using like qt or WX widgets to build a
C++ application not to mention the
complex licensing model that goes behind
some of these that might cost you quite
a bit of money so what do you do what do
you do if you just quickly want to make
an app in C++ why is everything so
difficult well before we answer that
question let's step back a little bit
why are you using C++ to build an
application because if you're not there
are so many things you could use I mean
if it's just something simple then maybe
you could consider writing a web app
that runs in like a web browser that
would be easily crossplatform out of the
box including mobile devices and really
anything with a good web browser and if
you wanted to be more desktop focused
with that kind of ease of web
development situation
then why don't you just use something
like JavaScript and electron I hear it's
great for the more serious applications
you could use something like C and WPF I
mean yes you'll be restricted to Windows
only but maybe that's okay I could go on
the point is there are many different
ways to build applications you don't
have to use C++ and in fact I would say
C++ is kind of an unusual Choice unless
you're like me if you're building a
performance intensive application or
something that's low level or something
that really highly revolves around a
library maybe that's written in C++ and
using wrappers or whatever is just a a
pain and you want to just write an
application in C++ instead you know for
those use cases it really does make a
lot of sense to just write your actual
kind of application GUI part of
everything in C++ so as an example for
those of you watching this channel you
know that I build game engines a game
engine what is a game engine a game
engine is basically like this C++ core
or at least it is in most cases that
then has stuff built around it to
facilitate the production of games as an
example so since the core is in C++ and
usually that core will adapt to whatever
platform you want it to adapt to so
whether that be Windows Mac Linux maybe
mobile devices maybe consoles that core
is very intrinsic to the application
therefore it makes a lot of sense to
write any tools that might go along with
the core that really rely on the core
such as an editor which needs to
actually have like a viewport that is
the core running inside it as well as
adjacent tools it makes a lot of sense
to write that Big Tool I'm talking about
the editor in C++ now you don't have to
I worked at EA for almost 5 years they
have frostbite Frost Ed the frostbite
editor is written in C WPF it of course
uses the frostbite C++ core but the
actual tools are written in C so even if
you are writing a game engine of course
you don't have to write your tools in
C++ however as I mentioned the downside
with C WPF is that it's Windows only
which is okay for a company with
proprietary technology such as EA
because their development teams can just
use Windows and in fact in the games
industry most people do use Windows I'm
not talking about the Indie developers
with their cool MacBooks I'm talking
about like AAA developers usually run on
Windows now unity and unreal are two
very big engines very popular engines
that have the core written in C++ but
then also the tools or specifically the
editor is also written in C++ Unity has
a bit of a c thing going on with a lot
of plugins and all of that but the core
kind of rendering framework is still
there in C++ and if you want to be
crossplatform and if you are a game
engine that already has a lot of r
rendering going on in my opinion it
makes a lot of sense to write your
editor in C++ and to also be using a GUI
framework that uses like immediate mode
rendering using your graphics API the
reason being that you are a game engine
like you are rendering things in real
time you're doing Graphics intensive
work it's totally okay for you to use
that same tech for your application UI
anyway game engines aside what if I just
want to build an application C++ why is
this so difficult what is the easiest
way for me to get up and running that is
what I'm here for today I just want to
show you guys what I do when I want to
build an application in C++ how it's
incredibly simple and way easier than
anything else I've tried and out of the
box it's not only crossplatform
including like mobile devices and
consoles but it can also adapt to any
rendering API you might be using DirectX
9 10 11 12 OPG vcon metal and you only
have to write your code once and it's
completely free in open source doesn't
this sound too good to be true I am of
course talking about IM am goey or dear
IM am gooey which is an absolutely
wonderful immediate mode GUI library but
wait isn't IM am guey some kind of like
toy you know debug UI thing for like
testing out applications just something
like really simple that can't be used to
build big applications no it's not it's
amazing and it can do pretty much
anything now I will put a little
disclaimer here just because and that is
like I don't want this to turn into like
a retain mode versus immediate mode
versus hybrid kind of uis and like what
what the best thing to to use is I
firmly believe immediate mode uis are
just superior but I also acknowledge
that it does depend on what you're doing
my specialty is in game engines game
engines as I mentioned are very much
real-time rendering Dynamic machines so
for what I do I think it's totally okay
if you are trying to be extremely
efficient on some kind of low speec
embedded device or something like yes
maybe you don't need to render the UI
every frame and be all responsive and
stuff but I would argue that right now
in 2022 for most cases immediate mode
uis are just better but isn't IM goey
like really limited and you can't style
it very well and it just doesn't look
good no where do you no because you're
literally rendering everything as if it
was a video game like you can do
literally anything this is what Hazel's
editor looks like this UI is completely
written in I'm goey yes we did have to
modify some parts of IM am guy to
actually make this happen but we are
still using IM am guy and it is still
great to be honest the only area where I
start to see problems with IM are
like if you have absolutely huge data
sets if they're all being kind of
rendered refreshed every frame you might
run into some problems but there are
always strategies to mitigate that you
can just use caching in some form
however in our experience in Hazel like
for example if we have like hundreds of
thousands of objects in the scene or
something the bottleneck has always been
our Cod so for example like we need to
show
details in a tree View and to get those
details we have to hit like the asset
manager and other Engine Systems to
retrieve those details those have
usually been the bottleneck not the I am
gooey rendering code my point is it's
very fast anyway enough talking this has
been quite the lecture but I just wanted
to explain to you guys what is going on
in a minute we're going to dive in and
take a look at how to actually write an
application in I'm goi but first I want
to mention that this video is sponsored
by hostinger hosting is pretty much the
best web hosting platform on the
internet if you need to host a website
or if you need a server for something to
do on the inter internet hosting it is
your go-to maybe you don't need to use
C++ to write your application maybe you
can write it as a web app how are you
going to host that web app using
hostinger we use hostinger to hos Hazel
engine.com which by the way you can go
to to find out more information about
hazel the game engine that we're
building setting up Hazel engine.com was
an incredibly simple process like you
just press a few buttons fill in some
details such as like you know the name
of your website pick your operating
system and it's pretty much ready to go
and that Simplicity applies to if you
just want like a shared hosting website
deal or if you're using a VPS like we
are and not only is the actual like UI
and dashboard and all of that beautiful
and simple they also have a ton of
useful documentation that will help you
get going or do something really
specific it's not only useful if this is
your first website I mean I've set up a
lot of websites in my day but just
coming in and finding out the specifics
of this web host in like just a few
words on their documentation is so
refreshing but I guess having such a
nice clean user interface and Brilliant
documentation you probably have to pay a
lot for that right no hosting his prices
are honestly insane they're honestly the
best value web host I have ever seen
click the link in the description below
to sign up if you use the coupon code
chero you'll get an even bigger discount
and I promise you you will not be
disappointed huge thank you as always to
hosting out for sponsoring this video so
as I mentioned let's dive in take a look
at how we can make a C++ application
using IM this is the IM guey GitHub
repository this is where all begins now
the only thing I want to point out here
apart from the fact that if this is your
first time you know you should read the
read me all that stuff maybe get to know
the library there are two main branches
there's a branch called Master there's a
branch called docking the rest are just
like feature branches but these two as
you can see are kind of like the main
the main events now docking even though
it's not the master branch is a very
mature usable branch that has been
around for like years eventually it will
be merged into Master it's not merged
into Master at the moment though and it
has a lot of really really useful
functionality such as a dock space so
that you can dock Windows like you would
in many applications these days as well
as being able to drag Windows outside of
the viewport as you'll see when I show
this later in this video so my advice is
to use a docking Branch now in my
opinion this docking branch is really
what makes imuy actually useful in the
real world for real applications if if
it wasn't for that kind of being able to
drag Windows outside of the main window
and also you know doc doc space all that
stuff uh I probably wouldn't be making
this video today recommending that you
use IM GOI for applications because
without this it would be a little bit
weird so let's obtain this I have
prepared a folder here it is called I am
guey apps uh if you just click on the
little address bar type in CMD to get to
a command prompt let's go ahead and
clone I'm goey and we will start from
there so let's go ahead and grab that
URL we'll go over here get clone I
always do a recursive clone just in case
there are sub modules that we need to
obtain I actually don't think imuy has
any but request clone anyway we'll paste
in the repository URL you don't really
need the dog it'll add it if it's not
there uh and then I'm going to check out
specifically that docking BR straight
away so if you do a-b we won't bother
checking out master and then we'll have
to switch to docking we can just check
out docking and then if you like you can
give it like a folder so I'm going to
call this my application it's going to
check out all of this code into a folder
called my application enter and now it's
going to clone I'm guey okay done that
didn't take much time let's go ahead and
go to that folder here we are here's my
application and we have all of our code
here now IM am guey works pretty much
anywhere because it has a lot of really
good examples and you can see over here
just how many examples it has if you're
just doing a speedrun and you just want
to get up and running with IM then
just open the IMU example solution pick
literally almost whatever you like so
for Windows I recommend either falcon or
like direct x 11 or 12 but this isn't
exactly a speedrun so let's talk about
this a little bit these example
directories have essentially like the
boilerplate examples for each platform
and library right so we have win32 like
directx10 for example this is using the
win32 API to actually like create the
window and handle all the events and
then it uses directx10 as the rendering
API as the graphics API so glfw openg
GL2 for example we'll use gfw as the
window and event library and all that
and then it'll use openg like version
two compliant code to actually do all of
the rendering there's even M script and
stuff here so you can run it on you know
the web uh there's metal so you can run
it this will probably just be a Mac OS
version but they do have like IOS and
Android example somewhere else here's an
Android example for example the point is
there's a ton of stuff here and then not
only is there this but they now have a
backends folder this used to be part of
examples that contains the actual
backend files for all of these my point
being that it's really easy to integrate
this with literally anything and that's
the beauty of this that's what makes
this so amazingly crossplatform the fact
that they just have example
implementations of everything and you
don't have to do anything yourself right
all you really have to do is open up
this IM Go examples. Solution now I'm
going to upgrade all of mine to like the
latest because I'm using visual studio
2022 and I think this is still 2019
let's go ahead and drag that into here
it's upgraded all the projects cool that
should be pretty straightforward and
then as I mentioned we pick something so
as an example I'm just going to pick gfw
Vulcan let's set that as a startup
project if we wanted to to keep things
clean we could unload like literally all
the other projects and I mean this is
where like if you were actually r
writing an application like you were
writing your own application using IM
guey maybe you wouldn't start with just
you know modifying this example solution
if you want to see a video on how to
actually create a project from scratch
using IM let me know I'll probably
do that but otherwise this is just going
to be faster so you'll see basically
five main files in this kind of example
gfw vcon main is the entry point as it
implies this is what has the actual like
main function if I can find it over here
right there's our int main it's got a
bunch of gel of w play code and see this
is where it's so amazing this is why I
love IMI so much as well because not
only is it an amazing GUI like Library
framework whatever it's also a fantastic
kind of example of how to get up and
running with all of these like apis like
whether you're using glfw for window or
sdl or win32 here's a beautiful example
of how to set up glfw create a window
set up Vulcan for it and then render UI
to it right so if we just hit F5 this is
going to be a debug build but it doesn't
really matter for us this is what we get
right this is basically ready to go
right we have a beautiful application
and as I mentioned because this is the
docking Branch we can literally take
this and just drag it out of the window
and you can see it's now its own window
this isn't possible in the main branch
or in the master Branch this is why
again as I mentioned like this kind of
functionality is great I can drag it to
my other monitor I can treade it like it
was a normal application which is
amazing and then under examples we've
also got that dock space right now it's
a doc space now I can dock this in here
and you can see suddenly we have a very
like real looking application but it's
all running in IM GUI it's all rendering
like you know well in this case at vsync
I'm on a 144 HZ monitor like it's all
rendering like real time frame to frame
every frame is is rendered from scratch
you know we have a good immediate mode
UI ready to go so how do we kind of
convert this into our own application
well from here you could literally set
up anything you wanted to right and
there's even some useful commands being
like you know you if you want your own
font because that's a common request I'm
gu's default font is a bit you know
debug looks like a debug UI thing um you
can change that easily obviously and
then we have like again very well
annotated the main Loop here so inside
the main Loop we have some important IM
gooey commands that have to happen at
the start of each frame so IM impul
Von new frame JF W new frame and then
finally I'm Guy's new frame once you
finish these three lines of code within
that main Loop
this stuff is basically rendering all of
the UI that we just saw so let's just
say we're not interested in this right
and then it goes all the way down to the
actual rendering code so that we also
need to keep so over here now is where
my code goes
here right so within this now we could
set up our own UI so to demonstrate this
in a little bit more of a kind of robust
way I'm going to create a new file and
I'm not sure where this will go exactly
because I don't know where the directory
is it's okay we'll just put it in here
um I'm going to go ahead and create a
new item and this is going to basically
be like our application like UI stuff so
I'm going to create a new file just to
keep it clean and simple so you guys
know what I'm talking about new file new
new header file there and a new CPP file
you know uh if I wanted to well let's
just keep this simple right I'm don't
want to be all Overkill here let's just
create like a namespace called my
app um and then we'll create a function
called like you know render U or
something like that nice and simple
let's go back to that C++ file there's
our render UI and then over here you
know as long as we include IM am guy and
I don't even know how this was including
in that Im goey so let's go take a look
okay so like this basically all we need
right over here now I can like create a
window so I'm going begin and you know
let's just say this is going to be my
like settings panel or
something I create that window I'm going
end to end the the window and then we
can like add a button hello let's add
like a drag float so we can have like a
static float
value we can have like some kind of
thing that we drag around this is just
an example obviously um that's our
settings panel done render UI so if we
go back to main let's just include that
application window or sorry that
application file that we just made
application. and then we just do my app
render UI F5
and we now have that settings panel I
talked about right but what about the
doc space so you can see there is no doc
space this is actually Vulcan rendering
a clear color in the background here
which again is is another perfect
example you know if you are in fact
writing an application that revolves
around Graphics rendering this is where
it's great to use IM GUI as well because
you you basically have all the Vulcan
boiler plate stuff done you can start
rendering whatever Graphics you like as
well as have UI stuff easily on top of
that um and that works really well
obviously so how how do we set up that
doc space in fact how do we do anything
in IM am GUI well Im am GUI has a
fantastic file called imuy demo.cpp
which is huge it's like 8,000 lines and
it has examples for everything that you
might want to do so let's let's go ahead
and simulate a scenario in which I don't
know what to do how do I create
something well the first thing is let's
go back to our app right I'm going to go
ahead and just type in am goey show demo
show demo window F5 right so now we're
not only going to get our settings
window we also get that demo window now
within this demo window you can just
have a browse so like Basics you know
here's like some stuff I might want oh I
want to make a tree how do I make this
whole tree thing right and because these
all have strings obviously that are
rendering you can just search for these
strings within the file so for example
basic trees let's go to that IM demo
file and search for basic trees here it
is right and we have a again the actual
code that was used to render this
specific like tree so again as an
example we know that we have a doc space
somewhere here and it's G gone ahead and
made it on the main window here so let's
just search for Doc space this is an
example for docking and docs space right
so show example app docs space so again
I'm going to just literally copy like
all of this now there's a menu bar here
and there's some stuff that we probably
don't care about but let's just copy the
whole thing anyway we'll go back to
application
I'll put it at the at the beginning here
so then we'll just strip it so what
don't I want so like again P open is not
really a required parameter here we can
replace it with an Ono because we don't
want to to close the thing show docking
disabled message like we don't need that
stuff sure we'll keep the menu bar um
what's this a menu item again we can
probably just strip some of this stuff
we don't care about like help marker um
well this is the close option I'm not
going to have a close option done right
and then I'll take my settings panel and
put it within the doc space like that we
can get rid of the show demo window and
then suddenly just like that we have a
doc space we have this and guess what
it's now dockable so we can just dock it
over here again to uh extend the example
of a game engine let's just say I have a
viewport panel as well right so I'm
going to make another viewport window
going to go ahead and dock this uh into
here there's my viewport dock it into
the center and guess what I basically
already have like my game engine up and
running I just need to render my stuff
in Vulcan or direct X or whatever I'm
using to a texture to a frame buffer and
then just display that image inside this
IM goey viewport as just an I'm
image right that is literally done uh
and then of course if you close this and
then reopen it it's going to save old
layout and that gets saved inside an
imoy file so it's basically like ready
to go it's such a simple thing and and
because we've kind of segregated
everything into this application uh you
know into these two application files
let's say that I don't want to use
Vulcan anymore I want to use DirectX 12
right because that's I don't know for
whatever reason maybe I need to or I
want to or whatever I can go ahead and
just like grab these two applications
now of course this is not like the best
architecture like you probably want like
a static library or something with these
things but for now I'm just going to
copy application. agent. CPP into here
right I'm going to set that as my
startup project we can like unload that
Vulcan project entirely so it doesn't
get in the way and then again I'm going
to go into to main I'm going to
include application. H and then I'm
going to go into like the main function
you know I'm going to find my well I'm
go like render is kind of what I'm
looking for there's my rendering code
there's that example UI code and then we
have this same pattern you know DX dx12
new frame w32 new frame I'm going new
frame so in between these two let's do
my you know the my app render UI F5 now
it's building the direct X2 example
using the win32 API of course my ini
file like didn't get carried across so
I'll have to reset up the layout but you
can see that's that's it like that's up
and running but that's my direct Tex 12
example and of course if we wanted to uh
customize that text a little bit we
could just change the title to like my
app or something and then now we have my
app up and running with everything so
really simple this was practically a
speedrun I apologize if I went very fast
and as I mentioned this is not like you
know the best architecture but this is
just how you get up and running with IM
GUI really easy and from here of course
you can build literally any application
you want it doesn't have to have any
rendering right I don't want to I don't
want you to get the wrong idea like you
don't have to render 3D Graphics in this
viewport you can but you don't have to
you could this could be a calculator app
right it doesn't matter but the point is
uh it's just really easy to get up and
running works on every platform any like
device really um
and yeah I don't think I need to say
anything else but you know me I will say
something else uh if you want to
actually see where the app was like
created to and you want to distribute
this for whatever reason let's go back
to like debug or I'm just going to one
of these things to see where the exe
file was output to let me just make that
a little bit wider so you can see I like
to use this output console sometimes to
just quickly grab the path so this is my
exe file that we were debugging there
this is a debug build you'll probably
want to use a release build but anyway
here is my like direct x 12 example uh
let's actually do something cool though
I like that layout let's go ahead and
grab that IM inii file and we'll pop
it into this debug thing and overwrite
this one just so that we retain our
layout and that's it right we now have
our application there's a lot of like
debug symbols and stuff that we really
don't need um it all builds into a
static library right so this little my
app situation my app is now literally
just this exe file and this ini file
right if we grab that put into an
isolated directory so it's clear what
actually goes into this rename this to
like my app we've made an application
we've made a C++ application that is
like 2 megabytes again this is a debug
build so I regret everything it would be
much smaller and much let's actually do
that let's just build a let's make a
release build I just did a build all
which is not what I wanted to do let's
just build this specifically and again
it's just going to put it into um the
release directory here it is 473 Koby
let's go back to our my app and uh we'll
just delete that replace that enter
there's our release build up and
running done ship it it's literally
ready well actually we do get that
console window though so maybe I'll take
back my ready to ship thing let's go
back into the release uh configuration
here into link a system and we will just
set this to be Windows instead uh let's
go ahead and rebuild that now we will
get a linking error over here because of
win main I honestly the I'm I feel like
the win32 example should definitely
include that instead but you B have to I
don't remember the win main like
function but for Windows application you
have to use uh the win main entry point
so let's go ahead and quickly we don't
really need all of this fancy stuff do
we F5 to just double
check okay now we get um no console
being allocated there which is good so
if we go back to my app and uh go ahead
and go into release copy that you know
the
drill paste it in my app enter no
console ready to ship I Can't Believe
It's Not Butter I mean I can't believe
that was that easy if you want to see
some more content around I'm
definitely let me know as I mentioned I
can go a little bit deeper into how to
actually set this up from scratch not
using their examples but you know how
you would set it up if you had like an
existing library or game engine or
something like that or if you want to
see some more like styling stuff so how
to get it actually looking nice and how
to get it to look more like hazel all
that stuff let me know as well hope you
guys enjoyed the video hope it was
helpful to you hope this will help you
out with your C++ application
development if you need a website or a
web server definitely check out
hosting.com Cho the link will be in the
description below I will see you guys
next time goodbye
[Music]